Sometimes when we talk about management what we're really talking about is what management allows us
to do as a project manager.
So we're in some regards still talking about governance.
So let's take a look here at these management elements in governance and how that affects us as project
managers.
So how do we get to manage the project.
Are we allowed to do so in our last few lectures as well I want to point out that this is a bit unique
to your organization this is not a universal it's unique to the PMS organization.
OK so governance is talk about portfolios programs and projects.
Recall from earlier in the course that a portfolio could have programs and projects.
So portfolios programs and projects here have governance the governance.
Generally when you have a portfolio it's shared among all of those that it's the same approach the same
rules the same bureaucracy for portfolios programs and projects so you have a common approach to the
alignment.
So the project managers the program managers to portfolio managers there's a common approach to risk
that all of the projects in the program in the portfolio use the same risk management techniques.
What about performance are we using earned value management or are we using number of defects or Schaik
defects.
So what about performance.
What are the expectations for communications in the project the program and the portfolio.
So this is unique to each organization that you tailor it for what's appropriate for where you are.
Some management elements of government see think about division of work and talk a little bit about
that earlier.
How do you determine who does what activity and having some distribution of work load balancing so that
all of your resources are used appropriately in the project.
Who has the authority to perform the work.
So sometimes you have to certain certifications or credentials to do that type of work responsibilities.
So we'll be doing some roles and responsibilities in chapter 9 when we talk about resource management
Chapter 9 and the Pemba.
What about discipline of action.
Unity of command.
Who's really in charge.
The project manager the program manager the functional manager.
So we need some clarity here on who's making the decisions in the project who's really in charge.
And we'll talk a little bit more about that coming up.
A lot of that unity of command and the next one here unity of direction is going to be dependent on
the organizational structure.
So how your company is structured or your organization is structured a general theme is that the organizational
goals are going to take precedence over individual goals.
So the organization is more important than the individual when it comes to business.
So don't let that upset you just the way it is that with the organizational goals are supporting our
business strategy or business tactics individual goals may be why I want an opportunity to do that task
so I learn it more clearly.
But we have a deadline that we're up against so the PM can't put you know someone who doesn't really
know how to do that activity on an assignment that's going to push us for our deadline or could affect
quality or so which is not an appropriate time.
So those types of instances what we're talking about that the organization goals are more important
than the individual goals.
We want individuals though to be paid fairly and to compensate folks for their time and talent and that
it's fair in the marketplace.
And as I mentioned a couple of times what an optimal use of resources.
Some other management elements of governance to consider clear communication channels who reports to
whom and why so who reports to whom.
You have the right materials doing a construction project and you need the tile by the 15th had better
be there by the 15th because then your tile crew is waiting and that's time wasted and money wasted
and it creates a delay in your project.
So you need the right materials to the right person at the right job at the right time.
So a lot of logistics here we talk about getting resources to job sites and making sure that people
have the tools and equipment facilities they need.
Nothing more frustrating than you're there to work but you don't have the tools or the materials and
then that's wasted time and wasted money because you're paying for that labor to sit around.
So you've got to do a lot of the just takes and some coordination here.
Obviously fair and equal treatment of people in the workplace.
Clear security of work positions.
So you're responsible for this.
This is your swim lane.
And so that is the boundaries not only for that individual but for others to stay out of the way this
is what this individual is responsible for.
They own that responsibility.
And so we don't want managers as project managers especially those of us who have come up through the
ranks.
And you're very familiar with the technology that's a boundary for you as well.
They don't get in that individual's way.
That's their responsibility.
Safety of people in the workplace.
Obviously if you're in one of those fields where there are pure risk.
So safety issues are always a concern.
We want our team to be safe for our employees to be safe and not be hurt or injured.
Nobody wants that open contribution to planning.
So sometimes planning it seems like PMS will exclude people.
What the project team should be there and stakeholders should be there.
We want some inclusiveness not only for just you know a shared ownership but these are people who are
closest to the work that they have the ideas and they understand the best way to get it done.
So as a PM I want those people involved that want them to help create the plan that it's not a solo
activity.
And optimal morale.
I want people to be happy as a project manager.
I want people to enjoy what they're doing.
Take pride in esteem and what they're doing.
People will work harder and work better and with more joy if they feel appreciated.
And so it doesn't take a lot.
To be honest and tell people you're doing a great job and I love what you're contributing to the project.
I really appreciate it.
And I'm so happy you're on this project.
Does it take much to do that.
And it's really good.
What do you love to hear that if you were a team member so I encourage you to do that.
And that's what we want.
Part of our governance here.
We want some optimal Merauke
then we have the organization of project management so some rules that happen here and some governance
that happens here is the PM.
When I complete projects for others I was a client vendor relationship.
So as a PM if I'm part of the vendor completing a project for you we're building a house for you and
I'm the PM of that house project.
There's obviously a relationship between us but I have responsibilities to my business my organization
and I have responsibilities to you.
I have responsibilities to the government because there are city inspectors or code and whatnot.
So there are different responsibilities in that client vendor relationship.
There is some expectations in some legalities because we have a contract that both of us sit here to
think about completing projects internally.
So internally through a system this idea of management by projects where everything that we do is a
project the project team comes on to this project for the duration.
And its kind of like a you know a SWAT team for lack of a better word that we all come on and we focus
and this is the only thing we work on.
Were putting all of our effort and energy into this one thing but there are some rules and some nuances
that happened with that approach as well as some risk that can happen with that approach.
That we had this idea of completing projects as needed where we all have operations to do.
But here's a little project over here could be a big project over here.
So I need these four or five people and you guys get together and do this project.
So in that instance I probably don't have a support system probably don't have a PMO may not have a
lot of historical information or knowledge repositories to call on for my project and templates and
forms so sometimes I'm kind of fumbling around in that scenario because we don't do this very often
it's on an as needed basis customers to a project can be internal or external.
So you think about the idea of customers are always a stakeholder.
Are we talking about internal customers where I can just walk down the hall to talk to that stakeholder
or is it an X Journal customer where there's a little different relationship and how I might communicate
with that customer.
OK good job.
A lot of information here I know.
Keep pressing on.
I'll see you in the next lecture.